Hello everyone!
This another video by
Dr. Kristine Dennis.
For those of you who haven't
seen one of her videos yet,
Kristine is an experienced nutrition
and public health scientist
who joined us to research videos,
write scripts,
and now narrate her own videos.
You'll continue to see
videos from both of us
interspersed in no
particular order.
So happy Kristine is with us
to provide another voice
and expand our perspectives.
Say hi in the comments
and thanks for giving her a warm
welcome to the NutritionFacts family.
"Is MSG Bad or Good for You?"
Reducing sodium intake
by 30 percent
could save the lives
of more than 40 million people.
And guess what can reduce
sodium intake
by more than 30 percent
in standard recipes?
Substituting traditional salt
with monosodium glutamate,
commonly known as MSG.
But what about "Chinese
Restaurant Syndrome,"
reported in a 1968 letter
to the New England
Journal of Medicine,
characterized by numbness
on the back of the neck,
general weakness,
and palpitation?
One of the proposed causes
was MSG,
a common seasoning often used
in Chinese cooking.
Since then, MSG has been blamed
for causing
numerous adverse reactions,
including asthma, headache,
and neuropsychiatric disorders.
But is this so-called
monosodium glutamate "allergy"
a menace or a myth?
You don't know
until you put it to the test,
or in this case, many tests.
In a multicenter, double-blind,
placebo-controlled,
multiple-challenge trial of MSG,
130 self-reported
MSG-reactive volunteers
first consumed beverages
containing 5 grams of MSG
or a placebo,
and those who reported
two or more
of 10 different symptoms,
such as flushing or headache,
were then rechallenged
in a dose-response study.
Of the 19 people
who consistently responded
to 5 grams of MSG
mixed in a drink,
once MSG was given in a capsule
(therefore ensuring people
couldn't actually taste
the MSG,
which they could
when it was mixed in a drink),
only two people had reactions.
The researchers noted that
large doses of MSG without food
may result in more symptoms,
but no persistent or serious
effects were observed.
For context,
estimated MSG intakes in the UK
are about 0.58 grams per day,
and in Asian countries,
such as China, Korea,
and Vietnam,
where it is
a more commonly used seasoning,
it ranges from 0.33 grams
per day
to 3.8 grams per day,
which is generally much less
than the massive 5g or greater
single doses provided
in the challenge trials.
Yet, only 2 out of 130 people
who claimed
to be sensitive to MSG
had any more symptoms than
when they just took a placebo.
Given the controversy,
consensus meetings
with scientific experts
convened in 1997
and again in 2007,
and concluded that
MSG was harmless,
and no dietary intake limits
needed to be set.
But, in 2017, the
European Food Safety Authority
reevaluated the safety
of glutamate as a food additive,
and decided
to set a limit of 30 mg
per kilogram of body weight
per day,
which is exceeded by
most people every day.
This limit was based off
a rat study from 1979,
with EFSA citing potential
neurodevelopmental
toxicity concerns.
But even the author
of the original study
says they failed to convincingly
show such an effect.
And given MSG's
salt-reducing benefits,
might it be a-okay
as a much-needed tool
to reduce sodium in foods?
Now, MSG still has sodium;
it's monosodium glutamate,
after all;
with about one third the sodium
of typical table salt.
So, a better salt substitute
would be potassium salt,
potassium chloride,
which has the potential
to save even more lives.